PERSONAL INFORMATION

Pamela Isabel Inostroza Fernández

- Sint-Jansbergsesteenweg 101 box 00.11, 3001 Leuven, Belgium
- (+32) 484 15 53 36
- □ pamela.inostroza@datic.cl inostroza.f.pamela@gmail.com
- https://github.com/Pamelalnostroza
- in https://www.linkedin.com/in/pamela-inostroza-fernandez-a9275523/
- Skype pamela.inostroza

Gender Female | Date of birth 17 November 1983 | Nationality Chilean

ABOUT ME

I have long time experience working as an independent contractor mainly as a statistical programmer. I know how to organize my time so I can work flexible hours in a project. I'm a certified SAS programmer. Currently, I'm available to work half time due to I'm finalizing my master degree, preparing my thesis project.

JOB APPLIED FOR

Statistical programmer

WORK EXPERIENCE

October 2019 - Present

Freelancer

cApStAn, Brussels (Belgium)

Language verification and adaptations from English to Latin-American spanish of PISA 2022 field test questionnaires, including new Global Crisis Module.

September 2017 - Present

Independent consultant

DATIC, Santiago (Chile)

Consultancy business, focused in programming and analysis of large dataset of information using different software and statistical techniques accordingly to the client needs.

- Design, evaluation and reporting of survey results applied to large, medium and small companies in the commune of San Antonio, V region, Chile.
- Formulation and implementation of methodology to estimate the amount of waste (plastic, glass, metal, wood, cardboard) produced by direct and indirect import and export of products using chilean customs information.

September 2016 - September 2019

Statistical Consultant

Education Quality Agency (Ministry of education), Santiago (Chile)

Programmer of automatized process in SAS software. Generation of statistics, reports and clean data that support quantitative analysis research. Automatic validation of achievement test and background questionnaires items, from national and internationals assessments. Research of new methodologies and instruments for the actualization of Personal and Social Development Indicators. Report of study results through consistent visualizations.

March 2016 - August 2016

Consultant

Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean - ECLAC, Santiago (Chile)

Statistical researcher in Scholar Violence using data from Third Regional Comparative and Explanatory Study (TERCE) comparing results from different countries, co-author of Violence and Achievement Report for UNICEF. Validation of scales and analysis of indicators.

August 2012 - January 2016 Coordi

Coordinator & Researcher

Comparative Educational Policies Centre, Diego Portales University, Santiago (Chile)

Head of team, in charge of coordinate the application, validation and analysis of results of context questionnaires in 15 countries in Latin America and the Caribbean for TERCE study. Research and implementation of statistical methodologies, data analysis and co-autor of technical and results reports

July 2011 - June 2012

SAS Programmer

International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement, Data Processing and Research Center (IEA - DPC), Hamburg (Germany)

Management and creation of SAS coding to process large scale datasets from PIRLS, TIMSS studies. Syntax adaptation, optimizing and updating procedures. Macro programming for complex procedures, adapting data to different formats according to protocols. Cleaning data and formatting to posterior analysis.

July 2007 - May 2011

Statistical Analyst

National Institute of Statistics (INE), Santiago (Chile)

Research and implementation of methodologies for actualization of CPI calculation programs in SAS software. Creation of automatized programming allowing weekly validation of home-basket prices databases. Imputation of missing values using mathematical techniques. Analysis of Household budget survey to obtain weights used in the calculation of CPI.

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

2019 - 2021

Master of Statistics and Data Science Statistics and Data Science for Social, Behavioral and Educational Sciences

Katholieke Universiteit Leuven - KU Leuven, Belgium

- Machine Learning and Inductive Inference, Advanced Analytics in a Big Data World, Privacy and Big Data, Data management.
- Survey Methodology, Structural equations, Meta-analysis, Epidemiology, Concepts of Bayesian data analysis, Log linear analysis, latent class analysis and logistic regression.
- Generalized lineal models, Mixed models, Multilevel Modelling, Analysis of Large Scale Social Networks.
- Statistical software, Modern Data Analytics, Data Visualization in Data Science, Collecting and Analyzing Big Data, Methods of Corpus Linguistics.

2003 - 2007 Bachelor of Statistics and Computer Science Statistical Engineer

Universidad de Santiago de Chile

- Calculus, Algebra
- Probability and Statistics, Sampling techniques, Inference
- Linear models, Multivariate methods, Chronological series
- Computer Science, Operating System, Equipment, Database

2019 - 2020 SAS Certified Professional

SAS Global Certification

- Advanced Programming Using SAS 9.4
- Base Programming Using SAS 9.4





SAS' Certified Specialist: Base Programming Using SAS' 9.4

2018 - 2020 Specialization

DataCamp

- R programmer career track
- Python programmer career track
- Data Scientist career track
- Machine learning (Supervised, Unsupervised) skill track
- Text Mining skill track
- Big Data skill track
- Image processing skill track

PERSONAL SKILLS

Mother tongue

Spanish

Other languages

UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING		
Listening	Reading	Spoken interaction	Spoken production			
C1	C1	C1	C1	B2		
International English Language Testing System (IELTS) C1						

English

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user - B1 and B2: Independent user - C1 and C2: Proficient user

Common European Framework of Reference for Languages

Communicational skills

- Ability to work in culturally sensitive contexts and achieve results under challenging circumstances.
- Excellent communication abilities (active listener).
- Experience training groups in statistical and software matters
- Good sense of dialogue and skills to create consensus
- Responsible, committed and flexible.
- Understand the valuable meaning of working in a multi-disciplinary team.

Organisational skills

- Experience working in research, reporting and analyst.
- Experience working for chilean government and international agencies.
- Experience leading teams in order to coordinate the analytical process

Digital competences

SELF-ASSESSMENT						
Information Processing	Communication	Content creation	Safety	Problem solving		
Proficient user	Proficient user	Proficient user	Independent user	Independent user		

Digital competences - Self-assessment grid

Computer skills

I have advance proficiency using:

- Microsoft Office
- PT-X
- SQL
- Git

Statistical software skills

I have advance proficiency programming in:

- R
- SAS
- Python
- SPSS, JMP
- Mplus, HLM, MlWin

Data visualization skills I have advance proficiency using:

- Power BI
- Tableau
- SAS Viya

Other skills Love to travel and experience different cultures. Love plants, I always try to have at least one plant around me.

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

- Publications (2017) Trucco, D.; Inostroza, P. Las violencias en el espacio escolar. Santiago: OREALC/UNESCO.
 - (2016) UNESCO OREALC. Inequidad de género en los logros de aprendizaje en educación primaria ¿Qué nos puede decir TERCE? Santiago: OREALC/UNESCO.
 - (2015) UNESCO OREALC. Reporte Técnico Tercer Estudio Regional Comparativo y Explicativo (TERCE)". Capítulo 7: Análisis de datos factores asociados. Santiago: OREALC/UNESCO.
 - (2015) Treviño, E.; Fraser P.; Meyer, A.; Morawietz, L.; Inostroza, P. & Naranjo, E. Informe de resultados Tercer Estudio Comparativo y Explicativo (TERCE). Cuadernillo Nº3 Factores Asociados, Santiago: ORE-ALC/UNESCO.